Suppose towards a contradiction that there is a bijection
from the naturals to the set of reals, which
we represent as all infinite binary strings.
Next we will focus on the diagonal, which is
just another infinite string of 0's and 1's, and
therefore another real number, which we call D.
We can use this number to define a new number D star, which is just the opposite
of D, meaning if there is a 0 we put a 1, and if there's a 1
we put a 0. So, we obtain a new infinite string of 0's and 1's,
so by our assumption that our map was 1 to 1, this
new real D star should exist somewhere in our list. But we
know that it cannot be the first element in the list, since
D^* differs from this real on teh first coordinate
But it also cannot be the second element,
since it differs on the second coordinate.
It can't be the 7'th element, since it differs on the 7'th coordinate. And
so, it cannot be equal to any of the elements in our list
But this contradicts our assumption that all real
numbers would appear somewhere in our list.
This argument may not convince you, in fact many mathematicians at the
time did not accept such arguments. But note that there are multiple
ways of proving this, and in fact this argument was not Cantor's
original one. And in some sense, continuous sets do clearly have different
properties from discrete ones, so it makes sense that
omega, which is the limit of some
discrete operation, is smaller than the continuum
However, once we accept this fact that some infinities are larger
then others, we enter a bit of a slippery slope, where
we suddenly have to accept infinitely many increasing infinities.
This follows from Cantor's theorem, which states that given any set X, the
size of the power set is strictly larger than the size of X.